Guide to the Alexander Papers 1665-1883 (bulk, 1717-1786) MS 8
New-York Historical Society
Alexander papers
1665-1883 (bulk, 1717-1786)
New-York Historical Society
MS 8
28 Linear feet in 60 boxes
The Alexander Papers is one of four discrete but closely related collections, known together as the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections. The Alexander Papers consists of the papers of James Alexander, James' wife, Mary Alexander, and their son, William Alexander (Lord Stirling). Material includes correspondence, surveys of tracts of land, mostly in New Jersey, contracts, wills, deeds, conveyances, accounts, bills, receipts, invoices, sight drafts, time drafts, promissory notes, memoranda, writs, warrants, depositions, affidavits, briefs, legal opinions, legal arguments, judgments, minutes, and petitions.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lewis Morris Rutherfurd, 1884
Arrangement
The Alexander Papers are organized in twelve series:
Series 1: James Alexander, 1686-1764
Series 2: William Alexander, 1744-circa 1786
Series 3: Mary Alexander, 1726-1766
Series 4: Other Correspondents, 1697-1815
Series 5: Legal Papers, 1665-1817
Series 6: Surveys, [1681]-1804
Series 7: Court Papers, 1684-1818
Series 8: New Jersey Proprietors, 1707-1797
Series 9: Colony/State of New Jersey, 1674-1787
Series 10: Colony/State of New York, 1683-1785
Series 11: Business Papers, 1699-1813
Series 12: Miscellaneous Items, 1712-[1883]
Biographical Note
Biographical Note for the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections
Chronology
1691 James Alexander born in Scotland, May 27
1693 Mary Spratt born in New York, April 17
1711 Mary Spratt marries Samuel Provoost, October 15
1715 James Alexander arrives in New York
[1719] Samuel Provoost dies
1721 Mary Spratt Provoost marries James Alexander, June 5
1721 Mary Alexander II born
1722 Susanna Alexander born
1726 William Alexander born
1729 Catherine Alexander born
17?? Elizabeth Alexander born
17?? Walter Rutherfurd born in [Edgerston, Roxburghshire] Scotland
1739 Mary Alexander II marries Peter Van Brugh Livingston
1748 William Alexander marries Sarah Livingston
17?? Elizabeth Alexander marries John Stevens
1756 James Alexander dies
1756 Walter Rutherfurd arrives in America. Serves in the Royal American Regiment
1758 Catherine Alexander marries Walter Rutherfurd
1760 Mary Alexander dies, April 18
1760 John Rutherfurd born September 20
1767 Mary Alexander Livingston dies
1782 John Rutherfurd marries Helena Morris October 30. Walter Rutherfurd presents John Rutherfurd with Tranquillity (sic) estate in Allamuchy, Warren County, New Jersey
1783 William Alexander dies, January 15
1788 Robert Walter Rutherfurd born in May
1800 Elizabeth Alexander Stevens dies
1801 Catherine Alexander Rutherfurd dies
1804 Walter Rutherfurd dies January 10
1807 Gen. John Reid dies February 6, at the age of 86
1808 John Rutherfurd moves to Edgerston on the Passaic River
1809 Robert Walter Rutherfurd marries Sabina Morris
1809 Helena Rutherfurd marries Peter Gerard Stuyvesant
1816 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd born November 25 to Robert Walter Rutherfurd and Sabina Morris Rutherfurd
1841 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd marries Margaret Chanler July 22
1842 Stuyvesant Rutherfurd born to Lewis Morris Rutherfurd and Margaret Chanler Rutherfurd
1847 Peter Gerard Stuyvesant dies August 16
[1847] In accordance with a provision of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's will, Stuyvesant Rutherfurd changes his name to Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
1854 Margaret Rutherfurd born
1859 Louisa Morris Rutherfurd born March 31
ca. 1860 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd Jr. born
1862 Winthrop Rutherfurd born
1863 Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Mary Pierrepont
1870 Robert Walter Rutherfurd dies
1873 Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant dies
1879 Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant dies
1879 Margaret Rutherfurd marries Henry White, December 3
1892 Louisa M. Rutherfurd dies
1902 Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Countess Matilde E. de Wassanaer (nee Matilde Lowenguth), June 16
1903 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant born
1906 Alain Stuyvesant born
1907 Stuyvesant Rutherfurd dies July 4
1916 Margaret Rutherfurd White dies
1925 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Rosalie Pillot
1927 Henry White dies at the age of 77
19?? Lewis Morris Rutherfurd Jr. dies
1944 Winthrop Rutherfurd dies
1944 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant dies, September 7
1948 Matilde Lowenguth Stuyvesant (in 1948, Princess Alexandre de Caraman Chimay) dies, July 10
1954 Alain Stuyvesant dies, Februrary 9
For more information on some of the persons represented in these collections consult:
Biographical Dictionaries
Dictionary of American Biography- James and William Alexander, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd
American National Biography- James, Mary, and William Alexander, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd, Henry White
Dictionary of National Biography- John Reid
Books
Rutherfurd, Livingston Family Records and Events New York, De Vinne Press, 1894
Valentine, Alan Chester Lord Stirling New York, Oxford University Press, 1969
Related Materials
The Rutherfurd Family Papers, http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/nyhs/rutherfam.html
The John Rutherfurd Papers, http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/nyhs/rutherjohn.html
The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers, http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/nyhs/stuyruth.html
Alexander Papers - Account Books Relating to the Equivalent Lands
Alexander, James - Journal 1718 - 1769
Alexander, James - Records and Accounts Relating to his Services in Behalf of the Children of Governors Burnet and Hunter, 1718 - 1745
Alexander, James - Register of Cases, New York Supreme Court, 1721 - 1742
Alexander, William - Ledger, 1766 - 1775
Alexander, William - Account Books, 1756 - 1758, 1763 - 1777
Alexander, William - Battoeman's Book, 1756
Alexander, William - Papers Relating to the Disposition of Lord Stirling's lands in Nova Scotia, 1831 - 1838, plus Copies of Earlier Papers
Alexander, William - [Material concerning the legality of William Alexander's Claim to the Title of earl of Stirling] compiled ca. 1857
Alexander - Livingston - Moore Account Book, ca. 1774 - 1785
William Alexander Papers
Rutherfurd Collection
Lord Stirling Papers
Scope and Contents
Scope and Content for the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections
The Alexander Papers is one of four discrete but closely related collections. The largest and the smallest of the four collections, the Alexander Papers and the John Rutherfurd Papers, were originally a single donation, made in the late 19th Century. The remaining two collections, the Rutherfurd Family Papers and the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers, were donated separately in the 1970's.
Together, these collections chronicle seven generations of an extended family in New York an d New Jersey over the course of two centuries. The founders of the family were James and Mary Alexander, who married in 1721. James Alexander had merchant business, but was primarily active as an attorney and government official in New York and New Jersey. Most of the material in the Alexander Papers derives from James Alexander's legal practice in both colonies, and from his tenures as Surveyor General of New Jersey, and Attorney General of New York. Other material in the Alexander Papers documents Mary Alexander's merchant business in New York, and the business activities and pre-Revolutionary military service of their son, William Alexander (Lord Stirling).
While the daughters of James and Mary Alexander are underrepresented in these collections, their husbands are represented to a greater or lesser extent in each of the collections described below. The Alexanders' four daughters married men who were or would become leading figures in New York and New Jersey. Mary married Peter Van Brugh Livingston, Susanna married John Reid, and Elizabeth married John Stevens. Catherine Alexander married Walter Rutherfurd.
The marriage of Catherine and Walter Rutherfurd also produced a son, John Rutherfurd, who evidently inherited the bulk of his father's and grandfather's papers. In 1847, Stuyvesant Rutherfurd (a grandson John Rutherfurd and nephew of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant), changed his name to Rutherfurd Stuyvesant in accordance with a provision of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's will. Rutherfurd Stuyvesant evidently inherited at least some of the papers of his uncle. The Rutherfurd collections contain material created by or pertaining to the Alexander family, and the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers contain material created by or pertaining to the Alexanders and the Stuyvesants.
The material the Rutherfurd collections relates primarily to the landholdings and business undertakings of a wealthy and socially prominent family. The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers documents the activities of later generations of that family. By the mid-nineteenth century, the family had become more occupied in strictly leisure activities.
Various descendants of John Rutherfurd donated the collections described in these finding aids to the New-York Historical Society, and the collections extensively document the business dealings, professional activities, and family relationships of the Alexanders during the 18th Century, and the Rutherfurds from the 18th until the early 20th centuries.
Finding aids to the other three collections:
The Rutherfurd Family Papers, http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/nyhs/rutherfam.html
The John Rutherfurd Papers, http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/nyhs/rutherjohn.html
The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers, http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/nyhs/stuyruth.html
Scope and Content for the Alexander Papers
The Alexander Papers consists of the papers of James Alexander, James' wife, Mary Alexander, and their son, William Alexander (Lord Stirling). Material includes correspondence, surveys of tracts of land, mostly in New Jersey, contracts, wills, deeds, conveyances, accounts, bills, receipts, invoices, sight drafts, time drafts, promissory notes, memoranda, writs, warrants, depositions, affidavits, briefs, legal opinions, legal arguments, judgments, minutes, and petitions. The papers of William Alexander includes a few documents relating to the sale, sickness, and burial of slaves.
Series 1, 2, and 3 contain correspondence, personal papers, and material such as accounts, bills, receipts, and invoices, that document the merchant businesses of James, Mary, and William Alexander.
Series 5, 6, and 7 contain material arranged by type, and in addition to items that relate to James, Mary, and William Alexander, contain items that relate to other persons. In the Court Papers series, for example, no distinction is made between suits or cases in which a member of the Alexander family was a litigant or counsel and those in which other persons were litigants or counsel. Similarly, indentures (excepting servant indentures) to which one Alexander Family member was a party, are interfiled in the Legal Papers series with those to which no family member was a party. Surveys made for members of the Alexander family are interfiled alphabetically with those of other landowners in the Surveys series.
Most of the material in the collection pertains to, or was created as a result of, James Alexander's various careers as a merchant, attorney, and agent of the Council of Proprietors of the Eastern Division of New Jersey. Although James Alexander was intimately involved in the defense of John Peter Zenger who was tried for seditious libel in New York in 1735, there is no material in the collection relating to the Zenger trial.
Similarly, the collection contains no material regarding William Alexander's suit in the late 1750's to have himself recognized as Earl of Stirling.
Very little of the material was in original order. When enclosures could be identified as belonging with letters, the enclosures were kept with the letters that enclosed them. Thus, a deed or will enclosed with a letter would remain with the letter in the Correspondence series; the letter would not be placed with the deed or will in the Legal Papers series. The only exceptions to this are papers relating to the court cases of DePeyster vs. Prevoost (Box 50), and Medina vs. Het (Box 51). In these instances, correspondence and legal papers have been kept in the Court Papers series, because this material appears to have been kept as a unit by James Alexander.
In all series, William Alexander appears in the alphabet under the name Alexander, William rather than under the name Stirling.
Civil law -- New Jersey -- Cases.; Civil law -- New York (State) -- Cases.; Coroners -- New Jersey.; Courts -- New Jersey.; Courts -- New York (State); Crime -- New Jersey.; Criminal law -- New Jersey -- Cases.; Criminal law -- New York (State) -- Cases.; Iron mines and mining -- New Jersey.; Justice, Administration of -- New Jersey.; Land grants -- New Jersey.; Landowners -- New Jersey.; Practice of law -- New Jersey.; Practice of law -- New York (State); Real property -- New Jersey.; Real property -- New York (State); Textile fabrics -- England -- Specimens.; Women merchants -- New York (State) -- New York.; Accounts.; Affidavits.; Cadastral maps.; Cloth.; Conveyances.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Depositions.; Dockets.; Invoices.; Judicial records.; Land surveys.; Legal correspondence.; Legal files.; Letters (correspondence); Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Notes (documents); Petitions.; Receipts (financial records); Swatches; Warrants; Wills.; Connecticut -- Boundaries -- New York (State).; New Jersey -- Boundaries.; New Jersey -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; New Jersey -- Politics and government -- To 1775.; New Jersey -- Surveys.; New York (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; New York (State) -- Boundaries -- Connecticut.; New York (State) -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763.; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- To 1775.; Oblong Tract (N.Y.); United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763.; Alexander, Mary, -1760; Alexander, James, 1691-1756; Alexander, William, 1726-1783; Bartow, Thomas; Bell, Andrew, 1757-1843; Clinton, Charles, 1690-1773; Colden, Cadwallader, 1688-1776; Board of Proprietors of the Eastern Division of New Jersey; Council of Proprietors of the Western Division of New Jersey; Coxe, John; David Barclay & Sons; Dunstar, Charles; Dunstar, Daniel Donaldson; Hancock, John, 1737-1793; Johnston, Andrew; Livingston, Gilbert; Livingston, Henry; Livingston, Peter Van Brugh, 1710-1792; Livingston, Robert; Lyell, Fenwick, 1767-1822; Lyne, James; Morris, Robert Hunter, approximately 1700-1764; Murray, Joseph; New Jersey. Court of Chancery; New Jersey. Court of Vice-Admiralty; New Jersey. Supreme Court; New York (State). Court of Admiralty; New York (State). Supreme Court; Ogden, David, 1707-1798; Pacheco, Roderigo; Prevoost, John; Ryerse, George, 1703-1792; Shirley, William, 1694-1771; Skinner, Cortlandt, 1728-1799; Smitzer, Peter; Snell, Robert, active 1771-1774; Stevens, John, 1716-1792; Unicorn (Ship); Watson, William
- Series 1: James Alexander, 1686-1764
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 consists primarily of correspondence of James Alexander and papers relating to his merchant business. Letters sent by James Alexander (mostly retained copies) are arranged alphabetically by recipient, except in cases where the recipient is unknown. In those cases, the letters are arranged chronologically. Letters received by James Alexander are arranged chronologically. Letters that were unaddressed, but which are docketed in James Alexander's handwriting, are for purposes of this arrangement considered as being addressed to him, and are in Series 1. Letters addressed to groups of persons which specifically include James Alexander are also in Series 1. Retained copies of letters written by James Alexander to more than one recipient are arranged chronologically in this series. One hand-sewn letter book contains letters regarding the "Oblong" or "Equivalent Lands" along the New York - Connecticut border. This item is foldered separately in this series.
  Frequent correspondents to James Alexander include Charles Clinton, Cadwallader Colden, John Coxe, Daniel Donaldson Dunstar, a Mr. Dunstar, probably Charles Dunstar, Andrew Johnston, Gilbert, Henry and Robert Livingston, a Mr. Lyell, probably Fenwick Lyell, James Lyne, Robert Hunter Morris, Joseph Murray, David Ogden, Rodrigo Pacheco, John Stevens, and William Watson.
  Most of the correspondence has to do with land titles and surveys in New Jersey. Correspondence with Cadwallader Colden concerns an area of the New York -Connecticut border (the "Oblong" or "Equivalent Lands"). Letters to and from Robert Hunter Morris, Joseph Murray and David Ogden pertain primarily to legal matters and specific court cases. Rodrigo Pacheco, a London merchant, frequently shipped goods to, and received goods from, James Alexander. John Stevens corresponded with James Alexander regarding the lease of mines in New Jersey.
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. A - Covenhoven, 1721-1753 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. Cox - D, 1729-1747 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. E - J, 1721-1753 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. K - L, 1727-1753 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. M-N, 1730-1756 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. O - R, 1727-1755 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. S - Z, 1730-1753 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. Recipient Unknown, 1725-1753 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - James Alexander--Letters Sent. Retained Copies to Multiple Recipients, 1726-1753, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - James Alexander--Drafts of Letters re: Oblong or Equivalent Lands, 1741 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1717-1726, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1727-1731 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1730-1732 July (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1732 August-1738 April (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1738 June-1741 September (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1741 October-1742 December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1743 January-1744 May (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1744 May-1746 May (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1746 June-1748 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1749-1750 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1751-1753 July (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - James Alexander--Letters Received, 1753 August-1755 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - James Alexander--Dances in New York; Diary, 1730, 1741-1742 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - James Alexander--Warrants of Attorney, 1720-1740 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - James Alexander--Business Papers. Receipts and Powers of Attorney, 1715-1728 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - James Alexander--Business Papers. Invoices/Fabric Samples, 1732, 1738 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - James Alexander--Business Papers. Invoices Inward & Outward, 1724-1749, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - James Alexander--Business Papers. Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1717-1732, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - James Alexander--Business Papers. Accounts, Receipts, Bills of Exchange, 1723-1758 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - James Alexander--Business Papers. Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1733-1743 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - James Alexander--Business Papers. Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1743-1764 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - James Alexander--Accounts. Estate of Daniel Donaldson Dunstar, 1751-1755, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - James Alexander--Memoranda, 1731-1754, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - James Alexander--Memoranda re: Elizabeth Town Land Disputes, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - James Alexander--Memoranda re: Second Nine Partners Tract and Manor Livingston, [1686] (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - James Alexander--Address and Opinion on Paper Money, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series 2: William Alexander, 1744-circa 1786
  Series 2 consists of correspondence and papers relating to the land holdings, merchant business, and military career of William Alexander (Lord Stirling). Letters sent by William Alexander are arranged alphabetically by recipient, except in cases where the recipient is unknown. In those cases, the letters are arranged chronologically. Most of the correspondence in this series consists of letters received by William Alexander. Letters that were not specifically addressed to William Alexander, but which are docketed in his handwriting, are for purposes of this arrangement considered as being addressed to him, and are in Series 2. Letters received by William Alexander are arranged chronologically. Separate folders contain William Alexander's correspondence to and from his brother-in-law John Stevens. At least one letter discusses the sale of slaves. Other frequent or noteworthy correspondents include Thomas Bartow, John Hancock, Peter van Brugh Livingston, and Henry Laurens.
  William Alexander's business papers contain accounts, bills receipts, etc. pertaining to his contract to supply General Shirley's 1755-1756 expedition to Oswego during the French and Indian War, and accounts, bills receipts accrued during his trip to London in 1756. Other business papers pertain to William Alexander's interest in the Hibernia mine and Hibernia furnace in northern New Jersey, his interest in the snow Unicorn and his joint business ventures with [Henry] Livingston.
  Among the legal papers specific to Series 2 are indentures (1764-1774) of servants to William Alexander.
  - William Alexander--Letters Sent, 1748-1782 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - William Alexander--Letters Sent to John Stevens, 1747-1750 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - William Alexander--Letters Sent. Recipient Unknown, 1767, 1772, 1774, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - William Alexander--Letters Received, 1744,1746-1749, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - William Alexander--Letters Received, 1750-1763 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - William Alexander--Letters Received, 1765-1782 (No 1764) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - William Alexander--Letters Received from John Stevens, 1747-1750 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Includes a letter dated August 20, 1749, discussing the sale of slaves.
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1747-1751, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Includes account dated October 17, 1750, for sale of 12 slaves and burial of one slave.
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1752-1757 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1758-1759 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1760-1761 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1762-1764 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1765 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1766 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1767-1768 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1769-1771 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1772-1785 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts. Oswego Expedition, 1755, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts. Oswego Expedition, 1756 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts. Hibernia Furnace, 1756-1761, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts. Interest Account, [1766] (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts. Sugar Account, [1765] (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts. Ash House Account, [1767] (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - William Alexander--Accounts, Bills, Receipts. Livingston & Alexander, 1763, 1767 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - William Alexander--Business Papers. Lottery, [1760] (Box 9, Folder 8)